Finding Aid for the Synanon Foundation Records LSC.0342
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Films
  - Walker Creek Construction: Camera Original and Work Print, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_582_004; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:12:21) 445 feet; Dot matrix "STOP" printed in at head (over image). A few frames later, two small holes punched in frame at head. Camera issues near tail causing frames to blur out of proper registration. Frame counts printed on edge of film. / Significant base scratching primarily on one of the sprocket sides (and therefore not in the image much). Light emulsion scratching in middle of frame. / Uncut film. / Some tape residue on film from original tape. Printed in edge information: "Ektachrome EFB 7 Safety Film" with same date code. / Base scratching mostly on edges with sprocket holes. / Likely camera issues causing frames to blur out of proper registration. Single frames of black leader have been spliced in between throughout reel, possibly to replace blurred frames. / Mostly black film with short segments of content near tail. Single black frames have been interpolated. Due to fleeting nature of film segments, stock could only be identified as from Kodak without further information about stock or date. Likely 1972. (Box 582, Case 4)
    Synanon archive #133a-g. Inside plastic can labeled: "A-36 - W.C. Construction - Orig. + W.P. - Pic - 1972" Aerial shots of Golden Gate Bridge and the Walker Creek ranch. / Construction equipment at ranch. Men in overalls digging into dirt with shovels. / Duplicate of part a. / "Construct - Wk Print" / Pouring cement at ranch. / Building construction. / "6.00 NET"
  - The Synanon People Ranch: Work Print, circa 1969-1971; yrlsc_342_582_005; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:16:40) 600 feet; Beginning and end titles have emulsion flipped compared to remainder of film. Some cement splices and one tear required reinforcing with tape during inspection. Others had been previously repaired with tape. Some torn perfs and damage to single perf black leader used for spacing (but then run through double perf system). Edge damage mostly previously repaired with tape. Kodachrome stock only using for black leader spacing. (Box 582, Case 5)
    Synanon archive #143. "D-5 - People Ranch - W.P. - Pic - 1972" From a generation before end titles were superimposed to image of Chuck Dederich. Instead, they appear at the end on their own.
  - Chinatown Must Change Now: Composite Print, 1969; yrlsc_342_582_006; Aiches, Marilynn; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:15:38) 563 feet; Infrequent stickers throughout for editing or timing, perhaps. Low contrast image. (Box 582, Case 6)
    Synanon archive #186. In Palmer Film Services paper bag inside can. Bag labeled: "Title 'Chinatown Must Change Now' - Property of Marilynn Aiches - Feet: 563 - Black and White - (1) 7302 B.+W. Electro Sound Release Print - Client's old answer print" Student film made about protests at San Francisco State College (University, now) in fall 1968. Focuses on student group Intercollegiate Chinese for Social Action and their combination with Third World Liberation Front. Directed by Marilynn Aiches with David Hilberman (The Synanon People Ranch and othersl) as faculty advisor. This may explain why this is in the collection. No information about film available online.
  - Experiments in Living: Camera Original, circa 1971; yrlsc_342_582_007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:08:20) 300 feet (Box 582, Case 7)
    Synanon archive #140. "A-16 - Experiments in Living - Orig. Pic - Mag. - 1972" Coffeemaking for group of people. Synanon building (unsure of location). Sign on door: "The New Born Experience - Everyone Welcome." People taking care of babies. People talking in living room environment. Shots of same people walking in or out of an interior door. Communal dinner scene. All lit and exposed well.
  - Experiments in Living: Mag Camera Original, circa 1971; yrlsc_342_582_008; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:01:23) 50 feet (Box 582, Case 8)
    Synanon archive #140. "A-16 - Experiments in Living - Orig. Pic - Mag. - 1972." Woman putting sheets on bed.
  - Synanon History Lecture #1: A Roll, 1973; yrlsc_342_582_009; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:26:23) 950 feet; Mix of sound (PXR, date code 1973) segments with silent (TXR, date code 1972). Cement splices are all strong, but some have slight corners coming up that were not taped over. Small cutouts between sprocket holes likely made for print timing. (Box 582, Case 9)
    Synanon archive #185a. In metal can labeled: "A-40-1 [...] Synanon History Lec. - A&B Roll - Orig. - 1973" and "'Synanon History Lecture #1' - Synanon Orig A&B Ret. L#00638." Inside Palmer Film Services paper bag with no labeling. Synanon history lecture at Synanon Research University in 1973. Footage cuts between lecturing (with sound, appears to be video transfer to film) and audience listening (silent, appears to be film original).
  - Synanon History Lecture #1: B Roll, 1973; yrlsc_342_582_010; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:29:10) 1050 feet; Cement splice at head previously reinforced with splice tape. (Box 582, Case 10)
    Synanon archive #185b. In metal can labeled: "A-40-1 [...] Synanon History Lec. - A&B Roll - Orig. - 1973" and "'Synanon History Lecture #1' - Synanon Orig A&B Ret. L#00638." Inside Palmer Film Services paper bag with no labeling. Film consists almost entirely of black leader between head title card: "The Synanon Foundation, Inc. presents Synanon History, a lecture by [...]. Copyright 1973 Synanon Foundation, Inc. All rights reserved" and tail title card: "Videotaped & produced by the film department of Synanon Foundation, Inc."
  - The Synanon People Ranch: Composite Print, 1972; yrlsc_342_584_001; Hilberman, David, 1911-2007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:15:58) 575 feet; Some scratching on print, but some scratches also appear to be printed in the image. (Box 584, Case 1)
    Synanon archive #322. Inside metal can with Palmer Film Services label: "Title: Synanon, The People Ranch (1972) - Property of Synanon Foundation, Inc. - [...] - Running time: 16:30 - Feed 600 - Black and White - Sound." Inside plastic shipping case: "From: Film/SF - People Ranch - For ... (crossed out) - 6/25/73 - SM Copy" and "audio visual duplicate" and "People Ranch - Santa Monica Copy" Promotional film depicting life in Synanon ranch.
  - The Synanon People Ranch: Composite Print, 1972; yrlsc_342_584_002; Hilberman, David, 1911-2007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:16:40) 600 feet; Mold visible on original wind. Very warped. (Box 584, Case 2)
    Synanon archive #323. Side of can labeled: "103/15 People Ranch" Synanon Films label on can: "Title: Synanon's People Ranch - No. 40-15 - Property of [...] - Running time: 16:30 - Feet: 606' - Black & White". Promotional film depicting life in Synanon ranch.
  - The Synanon People Ranch (Short Version): Composite Print, 1972; yrlsc_342_584_003; Hilberman, David, 1911-2007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:11:06) 400 feet; Many scratches throughout on both base and emulsion sides. Film slightly sticking to itself during unwinding. Attached SMPTE countdown is color faded, but the film itself is reversal black and white. (Box 584, Case 3)
    Synanon archive #325. Side of plastic can labeled: "103/ 6 The People Ranch / Short / 1972". Palmer Film Services label on can: "Title: The People Ranch - Short Version / Property of Synanon Foundation / [...] / Running time: 10:40 - Feet: 385 / Black & White". Can also labeled: "Audio Visual 'The People Ranch'" Short version of promotional film depicting life in Synanon ranch.
  - Triptych: Composite Reversal Print, circa 1969; yrlsc_342_584_004; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:09:01) 325 feet (Box 584, Case 4)
    Synanon archive #310. Metal can labeled: "0 1/1 Triptych" "Title: Triptych - Bill Wagner / Property of Wells Fargo Bank / Running Time: 8.5 min / Feet 303 / Color" and "Viewed by Helen + Marie / Not a (S) Film" Three short scenes shot around San Francisco (Golden Gate Bridge shots) and featuring one man. Playing guitar. No title information on print beyond "Triptych" title card.
  - Treasure From the Sea: Composite Reversal Print, circa 1945; yrlsc_342_584_005; Walt Disney Productions.; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:11:06) 400 feet; Very dirty print. Some tears in edge throughout. GREAT COLOR! (Box 584, Case 5)
    Metal reel labeled: "#2 Treasure From the Sea." Metal can labeled: "03 Treasure From the Sea" "#2 Treasure From the Sea / Do not remove from shop - [...]" and "Non (S) Film Audio/Visual #44 'Treasure From the Sea'" Animated sponsored film made by Disney for Dow Chemical to extol virtues of magnesium as lightweight metal for different applications.
  - "Catholic Imagery Footage": Camera Original, circa 1963; yrlsc_342_584_006; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:02:46) 100 feet; Uncut film. Dot matrix punched at head: "727866706". Punched at tail: "TXR" (Box 584, Case 6)
    Inside Kodak TXR 455 (Tri-X Reversal Movie Film) box. Handwritten: "Reel X" and labeled #21, "Non-(S) Film / Art Film #63." Develop before Jan 1965. Shots of various Catholic imagery, including a crucifix, cross, and the 1615 painting of St. Sebastian by Guido Reni. In various close-ups. Possibly all shot at one church?
  - "Wedding Festival News Footage": Mag Camera Original, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_586_001; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:11:06) 400 feet; Gevaert stock is only b/w countdown at head. Remainder of film is color reversal without edge information, perhaps Kodachrome? Bright color. Magnetic stripe in very poor condition, sticking to film underneath and in many cases, peeling off onto film underneath. At tail (center of original wind), majority of mag has peeled off. (Box 586, Case 1)
    Synanon archive #200. In padded "Jiffy" envelope address to [...], KSFO, [...]. KPIX 5 address label. Handwritten on label: "Wedding - Do Not Project." Postmarked in San Francisco, August 15, 1972. Appears to be news coverage from KPIX 5 (microphone visible in interviews) of the Wedding Festival. This footage does not appear to match that in "The Synanon Wedding Festival."
  - The House on the Beach: Composite Print (Reel 1 of 2), 1965; yrlsc_342_587_001; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:30:33) 1100 feet; Some minor rough edges, but nothing broken or torn. Repeated scuff on emulsion side. Uncut film. This print is from 1973. (Box 587, Case 1)
    Synanon archive #276. Lid has Palmer Film Services label: "Title: "#18-5 House on the Beach - Reel 1 / Property of: Synanon Foundaction, Inc. / [...] / Running time: 52:20 / Black and white / Sound" Also labeled: "Archives Film Circulation Library" Side of can labeled: "18.5 House of the Beach / Reel 1" Original reel labeled: "Intertel #31 / House on The Beach R-1" Note inside can: "Purchased from University of Indiana July 1973" Documentary on Synanon produced in 1965 by Rediffusion Television and Intertel for distribution by WNET. More information on American Archive of Public Broadcasting website: https://americanarchive.org/catalog/cpb-aacip_75-20sqvd1d
  - The House on the Beach: Composite Print (Reel 2 of 2), 1965; yrlsc_342_587_002; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:22:13) 800 feet; Some minor rough edges, but nothing broken or torn. Repeated scuff on emulsion side. Uncut film. Silver mirroring on segment at tail, appears to be short bit of black acetate film spliced in as leader. (Box 587, Case 2)
    Documentary on Synanon produced in 1965 by Rediffusion Television and Intertel for distribution by WNET.
  - Alcohol, Drugs or Alternatives: Composite Print, circa 1975; yrlsc_342_587_003; Sandler Institutional Films; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:25:00) 900 feet; Faded color. Light emulsion scratching on left side of image. (Box 587, Case 3)
    Educational film produced by Sandler Institutional Films. Does not appear to have direct connection to Synanon except for subject matter. Study guide insert for film including content description, viewing objectives, topics for discussion, and related activities. Card specifying print was purchased new from Sandler Institutional Films for $300 ($330 list price, less "special preview discount" of $30). Card for mailing back preview evaluation to Sandler.
  - The Synanon People Ranch: Composite Print, 1972; yrlsc_342_587_004; Hilberman, David, 1911-2007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:16:40) 600 feet; Emulsion scratches range from relatively light to medium throughout reel. Some rough edges near head, but nothing broken or torn. Removed yellow tape at head of film (printed leader), only tiny bit of residue remains. Redox blemishes where tape was. (Box 587, Case 4)
    Printed-in handwriting at head and tail: "People Ranch - Synanon Foundation" Green original head leader: "The People Ranch" Promotional film depicting life in Synanon ranch.
  - Jazz Scene USA - Sounds of Synanon: Composite Print, 1962; yrlsc_342_587_005; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:26:23) 950 feet; Significantly warped throughout and fairly dirty. Light scratches visible. Small section of black leader spliced in ~400' into reel (possibly for commercial break). Inscribed changeover cues at tail. More frequent splices at head than throughout reel, but all splices are strong, cement. A few minor perf tears in head countdown. (Box 587, Case 5)
    Printed-in handwriting at head and tail: "CBS-TVR Meadowlane Prod. Jazz Scene #7" and "CBS - Jazz Scene #7" Tail leader: "Jazz Scene / Sounds of Synanon" Episode #7 of TV series "Jazz Scene USA" produced by CBS Los Angeles. Hosted by Oscar Brown, Jr. Features Sounds of Synanon band playing in-studio, including guitarist Joe Pass. Kaleidoscope optical effect during one song. Brown explains Synanon with images and reel includes "Life at Synanon" segment, which appears to match content of "Synanon at 1351" reel (yrlsc_342_723_005) Band interviewed with Sounds of Synanon LP prominently displayed. Last song is "C.E.D." and a picture of Chuck Dederich is shown to introduce it.
  - Tannersville: Camera Original Outtakes, circa 1968; yrlsc_342_589_001; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:13:53) 500 feet; Many segments spliced together, might be jumbled out of chronological sequence, orientation and emulsion side switches throughout. Some perf tears. (Box 589, Case 1)
    Synanon archive #206. Can labeled: "A-42 - Tannersville - Outtakes - Release Print - 1968" Sign: "Seminar 'Fish Bowl' 1pm Synanon." People talking in circle (playing Synanon Game?). Close-ups of someone's arm tattoos. Haircut. Likely all shot at Synanon's location in Tannersville, NY.
  - Synanon 4-H Club: Work Print Outtakes, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_589_002; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:19:26) 700 feet; Trims were spliced together, several sections of edge damage and torn perfs. Damage from masking tape. Some tape residue remains at head. Many spots of redox blemishes throughout reel from tape originally used to connect trims. (Box 589, Case 2)
    Synanon archive #216. Consists of many different rolls combined together with identifying leader slug in between. They are: 216a - 4-H Animals Outtakes 1972; 216b - Parade 1972 (4-H); 216c - 4-H Prep for Showing WP Out; 216d - 4-H WP Outs Eating at Fair; 216e - 4-H WP Outs Showing 1972 Show; 216f - 4-H Animals Outs; 216g - People and Animals Out; 216h - 4-H Kids Eating Outs; 216i - Working with Animals Out; 216j - A27 4-H WP Oat Animal Eating; 216k - A27 4-H Working With Animals; 216l - A27 4-H WP Out Parade '72; 216m - A27 4-H Audience Out; 216n - A27 4-H WP Out Animals Eating; 216o - A27 4-H WP Outs Audience '72; 216p - A27 4-H WP Outs Showing '72; 216q - A27 4-H WP Out 4-H Sign; 216r - A27 4-H Grooming Animals; 216s - Medals; 216t - Goats Out; 216u - A27 Goats Eating WP Out; 216v - A27 4H Child Eating WP Out; 216w - A27 WP Prep for Show; 216x - A27 4H Awards WP Outs 1972; 216y - A27 4H Children Eating; 216z - A27 4-H Sign Ranch W Out 1972; 216aa - WP Outs People of Interest; 216bb - 4-H WP Outs Teaching; 216cc - 4-H Showing Sheep Oats WP; 216dd - A-24 4-H WP Out Kidwork W/A.; 216ee - A27 4-H Parade WP Outs; 216ff - A27 4-H Children Dressing WP Outs; 216gg - A27 4H Misc. WP Outs 1972; 216hh - A27 4-H Judging Animals WP Out
  - Children's Summer Camp: Work Print, circa 1971-1972; yrlsc_342_589_003; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:27:46) 1000 feet; Agfa dupe of Kodak Film. Three reels combined & separated with leader. Lots of temporary tape splices with residue - cleaned as best. Some grease pencil notation. (Box 589, Case 3)
    Synanon archive #s 128a, 128b, 128c. Primarily same content as camera original, but additional color & unknown footage in final reel. Third reel, 128c, previous inspected & spliced together.
  - Jitney Bunch: Work Print Outtakes, circa 1971; yrlsc_342_589_004; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:16:48) 605 feet; Appears that Eastman is print stock. Also printed on edges throughout are Kodak R 20 Safety Film (same date code) and Agfa Gevaert 1S 551. / Many short outtakes previously connected with flaking masking tape, occasionally labeled with trim number. Some tape residue remains and significant sites of redox blemishes, but sections have now been spliced together with short leader slugs in between. / Very loose original wind, falling off of two-inch core. (Box 589, Case 4)
    Synanon archive #215. Can labeled: "A-14 - Jitney Bunch - W.P. - Outs - Pic. - 1972" Tape on roll: "A-14 - Workouts - Jitney Bunch - W.P. Outs - " Tape at head: "Workprint - Outtakes" Mental health facility. People talking in rooms, eating lunch. / Shots of Synanon branded Mazda - possibly titular jitney transporting Synanon members. Santa Monica Maxda license plate holder. Some signs throughout: "The Palomar Co." and "Acoustic Control Corporation" and "Lifestylers Cart"
  - Synanon on Film - April 1972: Camera Original, yrlsc_342_589_005; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:07:38) 275 feet; Some minor tears in perfs previously repaired with edge tape. (Box 589, Case 5)
    Synanon archive #136b. Head leader: "April Synanon on Film - Pic Head Orig. 1972" First Anniversary in San Francisco, Synanon Camp - Badger, The Jitney Bunch ... Santa Monica (one frame title), birthday cake for Chuck followed by series of still shots of him, long list of credits at end.
  - "Wedding Festival Video Footage": Composite Reversal Print, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_589_006; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:19:26) 700 feet (Box 589, Case 6)
    Synanon archive #139. Palmer Film Services lid on can: "Title: Wedding Video Transfer - Property of Synanon - Running time: Complete - Black & White" Side of can: "Movie print of Wedding Video-tape" Video transfer to film with many instances of video distortion printed in. Features Wedding Festival (but not copy of "Wedding Festival" film). Instead, more casual perspective on event, with close-up interviews with many participants, including Chuck and Betty Dederich.
  - Cassette #2: Work Print, circa 1971-1972; yrlsc_342_589_007; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:15:16) 550 feet; Editing notes throughout made with marker or grease pencil. Very dirty film. (Box 589, Case 7)
    Synanon archive #170. Head leader: "Synanon: Cassette #2 Workprint Heads"
  - Cassette #2: B Roll, circa 1970-1972; yrlsc_342_589_008; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:20:08) 725 feet; Mix of silent and mag stripe film. Some cement splices starting to feel weak. (Box 589, Case 8)
    Synanon archive #169. Can labeled: "Cassette #2 - Synanon - B Roll Masterial Master Pic. 1973" Inside Palmer Film Services bag labeled: "Title: Cassette - Property of Synanon - Contents: B roll - 19966" Lots of black. Most content appears to be on A roll. Airplane. People outside Synanon Casa Del Mar building in Santa Monica. "Synanon's 4-H Club" title. "Synanon on Film" titles at tail.
  - Cassette #2: A Roll, circa 1971-1972; yrlsc_342_589_009; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:19:26) 700 feet; Film switches between mag stripe and silent throughout. Only color (Kodachrome) section is title card for "Female Boot Camp," otherwise all black and white. (Box 589, Case 9)
    Synanon archive #171. Can labeled: "Cassette #2 Synanon - Master Material - A-Roll - Pic. 1973" In Palmer Film Services paper bag labeled: "Title: "Cassette #2 - Property of Synanon - Contents: A roll - 19966" "Synanon on Film" titles at beginning. "Upward Mobility" title. "The Jitney Bunch...Santa Monica" title. People working in lab of some kind. Sign for "Acoustic Control Coporation." "Project Boot Camp...Tomales Bay" title. Men running. Footage of Synanon Game. 4-H Club footage. "Female Boot Camp" title.
  - Synanon on Film - April 1972: Work Print, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_589_010; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:07:38) 275 feet; Minor melt in film approx 40' in. Some broken perfs throughout, some previously repaired with splice tape and some not. Editing marks throughout made with grease pencil or marker. (Box 589, Case 10)
    Synanon archive #136a. Tape at head: "SoF - April 72 - WP - Pic" Head leader: "Work Print April S.OF Head Picture" Same content as yrlsc_342_589_005, but with "Synanon on Film" titles at beginning and missing end credits.
  - Instant Guide to Synanon: Composite Print, 1973; yrlsc_342_719_001; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:09:01) 325 feet; Color fading, but not too extreme. Lots of blues and green remain. Otherwise, minor wear to image, but print is in great shape. (Box 719, Case 1)
    Synanon Films label on original can, labeled: "#2 / Title: Instant Guide to Synanon / No. 115/18 / Running time: 8:45 / Feet: 313 / Color / Synanon Films [...]" Promotional film for Synanon styled as a Q&A.
  - "Wedding Festival Footage": Reversal Print, circa 1972; yrlsc_342_719_002; 1 motion picture film (1 Super 8mm film; Duration: 00:20:00) 300 feet; First few feet at head crumpled and previously repaired with splice tape, likely due to jam in projector. (Box 719, Case 2)
    Inside Kodak Movie Reel box & can. Handwriting printed in at head: "31081-0367" Shots of Chuck and Betty Dederich at wedding festival.
  - Public Service Spots: Synanon Foundation, Inc., undated; yrlsc_342_719_003; 1 sound recordings (1 vinyl record) 7 inch (Box 719, Case 3)
    Spots from Natalie Wood and Chuck Connors.
  - Synanon Group Picture: Camera Original, circa 1962; yrlsc_342_719_004; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:02:05) 75 feet; Tape splices are strong, but there are significant gaps between ends of film spliced together. In some cases, perf has been created in tape between film. (Box 719, Case 4)
    Synanon archive #104. Palmer Film Services label on can: "....out-takes..... / Title: Group Picture - 1962 / Property of Synanon Foundation, Inc. - [...] / Running time: 2:52 W-9 / Silent Black & White" Side of can labeled: "12. Synanon Group Picture 1962" Group picture outside Synanon House at old National Guard armory building in Santa Monica.
  - Halloween Party: Camera Original, circa 1971; yrlsc_342_719_005; 1 motion picture film (1 16mm film; Duration: 00:04:10) 150 feet (Box 719, Case 5)
    Synanon archive #184. Palmer Film Services label on can: "#34 Title: Halloween Party / Property of: Synanon - Lot by [...] / Running time: 12 min 20 sec / Feel: 143 / Black and white" Side of can labeled: "34. Halloween Party 1972" Note inside can: "Halloween Party - Oakland 1971 / Filming of poor quality and uninteresting"